<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A True relation or journal of the siege and taking by storm of the famous city of Belgrade by the Christian army under the conduct of the victorious elector of Bavaria, on the 6th day of September, 1688 with an account of its scituation, fortifications, &amp;c., and also of the great victory gained by Prince Lovis of Baden over the Turkish army, commanded by the Bassa of Bosnia.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95299</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3083</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42945</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875973</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875973</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152466</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95299)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152466)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2297:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A True relation or journal of the siege and taking by storm of the famous city of Belgrade by the Christian army under the conduct of the victorious elector of Bavaria, on the 6th day of September, 1688 with an account of its scituation, fortifications, &amp;c., and also of the great victory gained by Prince Lovis of Baden over the Turkish army, commanded by the Bassa of Bosnia.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 23 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Baldwin, and are to be sold by most Booksellers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures:</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Austro-Turkish War, 1683-1699.</term>
               <term>Belgrade (Serbia) --  History --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:152466:1"/>
            <p>Licenſed according to Order.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152466:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A True <hi>Relation or Journal</hi> OF THE Siege and Taking by Storm, The Famous CITY of Belgrade, BY THE Chriſtian Army, Under the Conduct of the Victorious Elector of BAVARIA.</p>
            <p>On the 6<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> day of <hi>September.</hi> 1688.</p>
            <p>With an Account of its Scituation, Fortifications, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And alſo of the great Victory gained by Prince <hi>Lovis</hi> of <hi>Baden,</hi> over the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Army, Commanded by the Baſſa of <hi>Boſnia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin;</hi> And are to be Sold by moſt Bookſellers. 1688.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:152466:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152466:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A True Relation Of the Siege of BELGRADE, With the Taking it by Storm, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>BElgrade</hi> is a City of Antient ſtanding and great Fame, Situate on the Confluence of the Rivers <hi>Saw</hi> or <hi>Save,</hi> and the <hi>Danube,</hi> and hath gone under divers Names; being at firſt, as far as can be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered from Hiſtory, called, <hi>Taururum,</hi> or <hi>Tauranum;</hi> after that, <hi>Alba Graeca;</hi> by the <hi>Dutch</hi> accordingly, <hi>Greichs-Weſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg;</hi> but by the <hi>French</hi> and Modern Latiniſts, <hi>Belgrade,</hi> and <hi>Belgradum;</hi> a Name given to this Important place for its Beautiful Situation, as being Hemm'd in upon the <hi>North</hi> with the <hi>Danube,</hi> on the <hi>Eaſt</hi> with the <hi>Saw</hi> or <hi>Save,</hi> and on the other parts ſtrongly ſecured with Walls, Bulwarks, Ramports, and deep Ditches, anciently belonging to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpots or Princes of <hi>Servia,</hi> tho lying on the very Frontiers of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and by many Attributed a City of that Kingdom,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152466:3"/>and may properly be divided into City and Suburbs; the Former having ſtanding in it a very high and ſtrong Caſtle, incompaſſed with double Walls, and what other Fortifications may contribute to its Defence. The Latter Repleniſhed with many goodly Fabricks, and curious Buildings, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixed with pleaſant Gardens, and has a proſpect of the Countries round it, almoſt from <hi>Buda</hi> to <hi>Adrianople;</hi> and of ſuch Importance was it in times paſt, That in <hi>Anno</hi> 1440. <hi>Amurath</hi> the Second Emperor of the <hi>Turks,</hi> after he had waſted <hi>Hungary,</hi> and ſeized upon <hi>Servia</hi> (during the Diſcontents and Inteſtine Broils of thoſe Countries) found nevertheleſs a check or ſtop to the progreſs of his Arms before this City; for having layn before it Seven Months, and loſt in the ſeveral Attacques and Sallies of the Beſieged 30000 Men; finding all hopes of taking it vain, he in a great Rage raiſed the Siege, and returned to <hi>Adrianople;</hi> ſo that the place had reſt till <hi>Anno</hi> 1456, at what time <hi>Mahomet</hi> the Great being Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror of the <hi>Turks,</hi> he upon the Death of <hi>George</hi> the Deſpot or Prince, ſeized upon <hi>Servia,</hi> which <hi>Amurath</hi> had permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be held by that Prince as Tributary to the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror; and paſſing on with a powerful Army, all the Cities and Towns but this opening their Gates, he laid Siege to it by Land and Water, and brought down a great many Veſſels and Gallies of War upon the <hi>Danube;</hi> though at that time the great <hi>Hunniades</hi> having been Elected King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and not well brooking to have ſo powerful a Neighbour, ſet out from <hi>Buda</hi> with many armed Veſſels, and falling ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the <hi>Turks</hi> Naval Forces, Burn'd, Sunk, and took moſt of them; upon notice whereof, <hi>Mahomet</hi> in a great Rage gave order for a general Aſſault, Vowing not to ſpare, nor give Quarter to any, if the City of <hi>Belgrade</hi> fell into his Hands; and after Six hours obſtinate Attempts, in which were loſt 4000. Men, one whereof was <hi>Curaizis Baſſa</hi> his Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in <hi>Europe,</hi> who was ſlain with a great Shot, he found
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152466:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>himſelf conſtrained to ſound the Retreat; and in the End, after many unſucceſsful Aſſaults, finding his Army weakened by the loſs of 40000 Men, he raiſed the Siege. From which time we find nothing Memorable relating to this City, till the Year 1520, at which time <hi>Solyman</hi> the Magnificent ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding <hi>Solyman</hi> his Father in the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Throne, quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> (into whoſe Protection <hi>Belgrade</hi> was taken, conſign'd by the Deſpot of <hi>Servia</hi> to King <hi>Sigiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund,</hi> as beſt able to Maintain it, in conſideration of Lands and Territories more remote) he laid Siege to it, being but weakly Garriſon'd, and worſe provided with Stores and Ammunition; and the King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> by reaſon of Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine Diviſions, being in no Capacity to raiſe an Army ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to Relieve it, the Beſieged found themſelves (after a ſhort Reſiſtance) conſtrained to deliver up the place that had ſo long ſtood the Bulwark of Chriſtendom, and has ever ſince been very advantageous to the Turks, by being made their chiefeſt Magazine or Store in the Weſtern parts of their Empire; and although the Chriſtians had many Conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions about Recovering it, yet ſoon after <hi>Buda</hi> being ſeized by the ſame <hi>Solyman,</hi> and other places of ſtrong Importance, the <hi>Turks</hi> poſſeſſed it quietly till this preſent year 1688, when on the Sixth of <hi>September</hi> after, having ſuſtained a Siege very Bloody and Reſolute, it was taken by Storm by the Imperial Forces, under the Command of the Victorious Elector of <hi>Bavaria.</hi> A True and Impartial Account of which take as followeth.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Lorain,</hi> by reaſon of his Indiſpoſition, not being capable to take the Field ſo early as the occaſion of bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs required, his Electoral Highneſs of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> offered his Service to the Emperor to lead the Army, which being accepted and approved, after the Forces were drawn out of their Winter Quarters and united, the Elector Arrived at
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152466:4"/>
               <hi>Vienna;</hi> and there making a ſhort ſtay, proceeded to his Command, when in a Council of War it was reſolved, That ſeeing <hi>Buda</hi> was already reduced, and Heaven ſignally favour'd the Chriſtian Arms, it was not convenient to omit the opportunity of Beſieging ſo Important a place the Infidels held, <hi>viz. Belgrade;</hi> whereupon the Army had order to March towards the <hi>Saw</hi> or <hi>Save;</hi> ſo that on the Fourth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> New Stile, they ſet forward from <hi>Salankamen</hi> to <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> where they ſtayed the next day; and the Sixth Encam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped at <hi>Semlyn;</hi> on the Seventh they came within Sight of the River, where it makes the conſiderable Iſlands of <hi>Zingari;</hi> when coming to the hither Bank, they perceived by reaſon of the Works the <hi>Turks</hi> had caſt up in the Iſlands, where <hi>Teckely</hi> was ſaid to be in Perſon, and on the further Shore, it was a matter of great difficulty, if not impoſſible, to paſs there, as had been before deſigned, being much broader than it had been Repreſented; ſo that ſome time being ſpent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout viewing, and further conſulting what was to be done, another place was fixed upon, and accordingly (the next day) a great number of Boats that had been brought thither up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Wheels, were put into the Water, and the Regiment of <hi>Staremberg,</hi> the Electors Guards, and four Thouſand Men, Detached out of other Bodies, were ordered to Waft over, under the Command of the Valiant, and truly Heroick, Count <hi>Serini,</hi> General of the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Forces; when about Nine at Night, the Drums and Hautboys of the <hi>Janizaries</hi> were heard in the Camp, as ſeeming to approach the place of paſſage; but it ſo little diſcouraged the Imperialiſts, that about Eleven at Night, the Foot were Embarqued, and the Elector directed that 500 Men, under the Command of a Lieutenant Colonel, ſhould Land firſt to obſerve the place; but ſcarce were they in the Middle of the River, but about 300 <hi>Turks</hi> appeared on the further Shore, and diſcharged a Volley of Shot, but without doing any dammage to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152466:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>who, after this diſcharge, haſtened to Land under the favour of the Cannon Planted to Annoy the Enemy; ſo that thereupon the <hi>Turks</hi> quitted their Poſt; where the Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing place and ground was found as well as could reaſonably be wiſhed, being very Commodious, by reaſon about four paces from the Bank of the River were almoſt Inacceſſible, by reaſon of the Buſhes and Woody places; ſo that the Boats left thoſe they carried over in Security, and returned; when about Four in the Morning, 3000 were got over, covering and Intrenching themſelves, to prevent any Attempt or Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize the Evening might make upon them, who now ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached in conſiderable Numbers; and whilſt the Foot thus continued to paſs over in Boats, the Bridge was laid for the Horſe; however, before it could be Finiſhed, 6000 of the Enemies Foot, and ſome Horſe, Attacqued the Chriſtians on the further Shoar, on the Right and the Left; but, after ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Aſſaults, were Repulſed with a conſiderable Loſs; the Chriſtians loſing a Major of the Regiment of <hi>Staremberg,</hi> with divers Granadeers that were too far advanced; when about Eleven of the Clock, 10000 Men had effectually paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the River; and then the Enemy appeared again with a greater force, within Muſquet-ſhot, but made no farther at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt; and ſoon after, a <hi>Hungarian</hi> Diſſenter, Informed the General, That the Enemy the Night following, intended to make an Attacque with their whole Power; but about Five in the Evening (the Bridge being entirely finiſhed) a Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Dragoons paſſed it, and after them, the Foot that remained, and about Midnight, the reſt of the Horſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo that on the Ninth of <hi>August,</hi> the whole Army, with the Artillery and Baggage, Encamped on the further Shore, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in four Leagues of <hi>Belgrade;</hi> where his Electoral Highneſs was Informed, That there was a Garriſon of 12000 <hi>Turks,</hi> and 3000 <hi>Tartars</hi> in the City, but without any certainty; and that <hi>Yeghen Baſſa</hi> lay Entrenched with the reſt of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152466:5"/>
               <hi>Ottoman</hi> Forces, between the <hi>Save</hi> and the <hi>Danube,</hi> to cover the place; but being nothing diſmayed at this Report, his Electoral Highneſs Commanded the Army on the Tenth to March towards the City, in order to Battle, reſolving to Attacque the Enemy in their Camp; when, contrary to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, they found it abandoned, and the Suburbs or lower Town on Fire, the <hi>Turks</hi> that Inhabited it, having ſaved themſelves in the Boats belonging to the City; yet four of them were taken with a conſiderable Booty, and the <hi>Huſſars</hi> being ſent out in a flying Party after the Retreating Enemy, took much of their Baggage, and ſome Thouſands of great and ſmall Cattle; when upon the near approach of the Army, 4000 <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Raſcians,</hi> with their Wives and Children, came to meet them, and to Implore his Electoral Highneſſes Protection, which they obtained; ſtrict Orders being given throughout the Camp, that none under great Penalties and Puniſhment, ſhould preſume to diſturb or moleſt them; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, the Soldiers having quenched the Fire, after it had Burnt ſeveral hundred Houſes, found a conſiderable Booty the <hi>Turks</hi> in their haſt and confuſion had left behind them.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> thus uncontrouled approaching the Walls of <hi>Belgrade,</hi> Scouts were ſent out to learn the Motion and Intent of the Enemy, who returned with an Account, That <hi>Yeghen</hi> Baſſa, the Seraſquier of <hi>Hungary,</hi> together with <hi>Yeck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,</hi> was retired to <hi>Sendrovia,</hi> about Eight Leagues further, with 20000 Men under his Command: And upon further Inquiry, it was confidently reported, That no more than 4000 Men were left in the Caſtle or upper Fortreſs, under the Command of a Governor, who had lately been a common Soldier: And further, That <hi>Yeghen</hi> would have Fought the Army, but was diſſwaded from it by the Baſſa of <hi>Erla</hi> or <hi>Agria,</hi> and ſome other Principal Officers; Three of which (in a great Fury) he cut in pieces with his own hand, and cauſed the Baſſa of <hi>Agria</hi> to be Strangled in his
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152466:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>preſence; the former Baſſa, Governour of <hi>Belgrade,</hi> making his Eſcape, to avoid his Fury; as alſo did <hi>Haſſan</hi> Baſſa, his Competitor.</p>
            <p>Upon the day of Arrival before the place, the Elector of <hi>Bavaria</hi> cauſed the Trenches to be opened againſt the Upper Town and Caſtle, and diſpatched the Sieur <hi>Dietrick,</hi> Captain of Horſe, and Adjutant to General <hi>Caprara,</hi> with Letters to <hi>Vienna,</hi> giving the Emperor an account of the Succeſs, and lodged himſelf in the Pleaſure-Houſe, built without the Town, for the Reception of the Depoſed <hi>Sultan Mahomet,</hi> when he came to View the Muſter of his Army that (under the Leading of <hi>Cara Muſtapha</hi> the Grand <hi>Vizier</hi>) Beſieged <hi>Vienna, Anno</hi> 1683. where he had News, that the Prince of <hi>Baden,</hi> after Three hours obſtinate Fight, had overthrown the Baſſa of <hi>Boſna</hi>'s Army, compoſed of between 12 and 14000 Men, poſted to hinder his Paſſage over the River <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na,</hi> Killing Four Thouſand on the Place; upon which, <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>towitza</hi> had Surrendred, a Place of conſiderable Importance on that ſide.</p>
            <p>Things being at this paſs, Preparations were made (with much caution and diligence) to Attack the Caſtle; the Management or Conduct of which, was left to Count <hi>Serini,</hi> Lieutenant General to His Electoral Highneſs, the Walls whereof the Elector had Viewed, and given Orders, where he perceived it moſt advantageous for the Attacks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And although the <hi>Turks</hi> Sallyed at the ſame time, yet were they beaten back, with the loſs of but One Man on the part of the <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next day, being the Twelfth, in the Evening the Troops' began to Approach the Caſtle, and to take their Poſts; to hinder which, the Enemy made a Vigorous Sally, ſo that the Skirmiſh continued Three or Four hours, but at laſt they were Repulſed; and in this Action Eighty of the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> were Killed and Wounded, the <hi>Turks</hi> loſing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152466:6"/>a greater Number: And ſo ſucceſsful it proved, that the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſecured, under the favour of this Action, their Poſts, and opened the Frenches within Muſquet-ſhot of the Walls, and began to work on Two Batteries.</p>
            <p>The Thirteenth in the Morning, the Beſieged made ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sally in a greater Body than the former, breaking on up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Beſiegers, and came to Handy-blows, in which Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute Count <hi>Rabntine,</hi> General of the Battalia, was ſhot in the Arm, Count <hi>Taſſis,</hi> Serjeant Major of the Regiment of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> in the Body, and ſeveral other private Soldiers were Killed and Wounded; but the Beſiegers being preſently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inforced, the Beſieged were beaten back, many of them being Slain and Wounded, of which 500 were left behind Dead, and two taken Priſoners; who Reported, That there were Ten Thouſand Perſons in the Garriſon, but many of them Women and Children, which was confirmed by a Chriſtian Slave, who had been there ſince the Siege of <hi>Vienna,</hi> and now made his eſcape to the Army; when the ſame day, News came, That <hi>Yeghen Baſſa</hi> had ſet the Famous City of <hi>Seman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra</hi> on Fire, which was about ſeven Leagues from the Camp, and carried the Inhabitants to <hi>Niſſa,</hi> continuing his Retreat in great diſorder towards <hi>Sofia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Fourteenth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> the Enemies Cannon Played ſuriouſly, and they threw a great many Granado's and Bombs, but did no conſiderable Execution; and after that, made ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sally, though with no better ſucceſs than the former; and the ſame day a Detachment of the Garriſon of <hi>Temeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware</hi> got by the help of Boats into the Caſtle, on that part that ſtands to the River <hi>Danube,</hi> though the number was not conſiderable.</p>
            <p>The Fifteenth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> the Beſieged had finiſhed a Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery of three Mortars, and ſhot a great many Carcaſſes and Bombs into the place, doing conſiderable Execution; and the Elector ordered, that a Lieutenant General, a Serjeant-Major,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152466:6"/>and Two Colonels, with 800 Horſe, and 3000 Foot ſhould Nightly Guard the Trenches; where, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to Incourage the Workmen, His Electoral Highneſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued frequently till One or Two in the Morning.</p>
            <p>On the Sixteenth, the Duke of <hi>Mantua</hi> arrived, and made his Entrance into the Camp with a numerous Train, and ſplendid Equipage, having with him above 500 Men on Horſe-back, including his Guards, 40 lead Horſes, 24 Mules, and 25 Waggons with Baggage, and a Coach of State drawn by Six Horſes, and followed by many other Coaches, and a great many Servants in Liveries; and upon his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, was met by the Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> accompanied by the Chief Officers, about a Mile from the Camp, and thence conducted to the Head Quarters, where they Dined together, and afterward went to viſit the Trenches, when in the mean time, his Tents to the number of 104, ſome of them very Rich, were pitched between the Electors Quarters, and that of General <hi>Caprara;</hi> and in the Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Beſieged made a Sally with a greater Body than formerly, but found the Trenches ſo ſtrongly Guarded, that they were obliged to Retreat with a conſiderable loſs.</p>
            <p>On the Seventeenth, by break of day, the Beſiegers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to Batter the Walls of the Caſtle with Six Pieces of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, and underſtood by a Deſerter, that the Enemy were hard at work in their Mines; and in the Evening, General <hi>Caprara,</hi> being with his Electoral Highneſs in the Trenches, to give neceſſary directions, and encourage thoſe that were working, a Muſquet-ſhot paſſed through his Hat and Peruke, without doing him any further damage.</p>
            <p>On the Eighteenth the Enemies Cannon and Small-ſhot played very ſmartly, ſo that Count <hi>Gallenfells,</hi> a Colonel of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> being in the Trenches, received a Wound in the Body with a Muſquet-ſhot, and Lieutenant Colonel Count <hi>Lambert,</hi> another in the Head, and the young Count <hi>De
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152466:7"/>Traun</hi> had his Arm ſhot off, and under the favour of their Canon the Enemy Sallyed, but were ſoon beaten back.</p>
            <p>On the Nineteenth, the Trenches were carried on with great diligence, inſomuch that the Workmen run them within ten paces of the Ditch, though not without ſome conſiderable oppoſition, and great loſs of Men, but not any of Note; ſo that now they began to raiſe two new Batteries, and the Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> Count <hi>Serini,</hi> and General <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prara,</hi> continuing all Night in the Trenches, the better to encourage ſo important a Work.</p>
            <p>On the Twentieth, the Beſiegers poſſeſſed themſelves of a <hi>Moſque</hi> or <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Church, on the brink of the Ditch, which the Beſieged upon their approach abandoned, and haſtened to the Caſtle with great precipitation; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, one leſs nimble than the reſt was taken, who declared upon Examination, there were 5000 <hi>Janizaries</hi> in the Town and Caſtle, and that the Commanding Baſſa encouraged the Garriſon with aſſurance of Relief, promiſing at the ſame time, not to ſuffer things to come to Extremity, though no great ſtreſs was laid upon this Report; ſo that the Canon and Bombs continued to play furiouſly on both ſides, where by one of the Shells the Prince <hi>D'Comercy</hi> received a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuſion or Bruiſe on the Arm, and the Sieur <hi>Claudio Martelli,</hi> Adjutant General to the Army, a Wound in the Head; and although many others of leſſer Note were Wounded, yet but one Man was killed.</p>
            <p>On the One and Twentieth, two Parallel Lines were drawn on the Right and the Left, to compaſs a greater ſpace of Ground, as well on the ſide of the Caſtle, as the Town, and two Redoubts made to ſupport the Heads of them, which were performed in ſpite of the oppoſition the Enemy made, doing all they could with their Canon and Bombs, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damage the Workmen, and hinder the Proceedings.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:152466:7"/>
            <p>On the Twenty Second, the Beſiegers having per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected the Works, the great Canon and Mortars Arrived from <hi>Buda;</hi> upon which, Orders were given to Batter the Caſtle from Two Batteries, one of Fourteen Pieces, and the other of Twelve: And a Deſerter that came into the Camp, reported, <hi>That the Baſſa had cauſed a conſiderable Officer to be Hanged, on the Fifteenth, for offering to ſpeak of a Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render: And that he gave, for their better Incouragement, a Duccate to every Man that would venture to make a Sally:</hi> And about this Time other Scouts that had been ſent out to obſerve the Motion of <hi>Yeghen Baſſa,</hi> returned, having been as far as <hi>Sendrovia,</hi> and made their Report, that the Caſtle and Town were quite deſtroyed by Fire, but the Walls are ſtanding; and that the <hi>Turks</hi> left Twenty Pieces of Canon behind them for haſt, or want of conveniency to carry them off. They likewiſe brought with them a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> who had made his Eſcape out of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Army, confirming, That <hi>Yeghen</hi> Baſſa was retired to <hi>Niſſa,</hi> about Twenty Leagues from <hi>Belgrade,</hi> burning the Country, and carrying the People along with him; ſo that care was taken to fetch off the Canon left at <hi>Seudrovia;</hi> And then it was Rumoured, that a great many Families of <hi>Raſcians</hi> had offered to Re-edifie and Inhabit that Ancient City, if they might be Protected by an Imperial Gariſon.</p>
            <p>On the Twenty Third, the Beſiegers batter'd the Caſtle very ſuriouſly, which is Built after the Ancient way of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying, with Towers, Battlements, Double-Walls, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Ditches; however, the Canon made divers Breaches, and beat down part of the Fortifications; and although the Beſieged Sallyed, with an Intent to Attack the Redoubts, they were beaten in again, leaving a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable number of their Party dead behind them. And about this Time it was further confirmed, that the Prince of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152466:8"/>
               <hi>Baden</hi> had routed the Baſſa of <hi>Boſna,</hi> and Killed 3000 Men. Moreover, <hi>Debitza, Jeſſuewitz,</hi> and <hi>Gradiska</hi> being firſt ſet on Fire, were Abandoned by the <hi>Turks,</hi> who were retired towards <hi>Banyalucca,</hi> whither the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> follow'd them: As alſo that General <hi>Veterani</hi> had Taken <hi>Carauſebes,</hi> and the ſtrong Caſtle of <hi>Salancar:</hi> And now the Canon Playing ſuriouſly from the Batteries; the Engineers (though they were raiſed as high as they could bare) found ſome Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, by reaſon of the Ruinous Houſes that had been conſumed by the Fire, or ſhatter'd by the force of the Bombs and Canon; whereupon the Miners received Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to Overthrow them: in which they were ſo Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and ſucceſsful, that the Beſieged were laid more open to the force of Twenty Six Pieces of Canon, though the Beſieged were not Idle but made very Vigorous Sallies, as long as they could, Playing their Canon, Bombs, and ſmall Shot without Intermiſſion; ſo that many were Killed on both ſides, and ſome Wounded; amongſt the latter was Count <hi>D' Ligneville,</hi> Collonel of Foot, and Adjutant Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, wounded by a Shot in the Trenches, whither he was come to give neceſſary Orders; and although he was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried off, yet ſoon after he Died of the Wound.</p>
            <p>Theſe being the Actions paſſing the Twenty Third and Twenty Fourth, and the heavy Canon being all mounted on the Batteries; whilſt they were Thundring againſt the Walls, a Letter was brought and Preſented to the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> from <hi>Oſman</hi> Baſſa of <hi>Aleppo;</hi> the Tenure of which, together with His Electoral Highneſſes Anſwer, take as followeth:</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:152466:8"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The Letter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Honour of Princes, Believing in</hi> Jeſus, <hi>Choſen among the moſt Noble of the Chriſtian Nation, Pattern of Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence, Poſſeſſor of all Splendor, Duke of</hi> Bavaria, <hi>and Chief General of the</hi> Roman <hi>Empire,</hi> Maximilian, <hi>whoſe ways be Proſperous; after Salutation, Be it Known unto You, That the moſt Serene, Great and Mighty</hi> Ottoman <hi>Emperour, Monarch of the World, Our Lord, having ſent with His Serene Letter, to the greateſt of the Chriſtian Kings, the moſt Serene Emperor, One of His Well-deſerving Servants</hi> Sulficar Effendi, <hi>Adorned with ſeveral High Degrees of Honour, whoſe Praiſe be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, and the Preſent</hi> Drugerman <hi>of the Renowned Port, a Mirror of the Nobles of the Chriſtian Worſhip,</hi> Alexander, <hi>whoſe ways end Happy. They are Arrived here, and becauſe they are going to You, and according to Ancient and Laudable Cuſtom, have need for Themſelves, and a Hundred Perſons, of Paſs-ports and Safe-guards to be ſent from your Army, this Our preſent Letter is Written and Diſpatched to You. After the Receipt whereof, We hope that Paſs-ports, and ſome People for a Safe-guard; will be ſent hither, that the above-mentioned may, as They are Commanded, Repair to You. They will, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Their coming near,</hi> (God <hi>willing</hi>) <hi>ſend again to You, to the End a Convoy may come from your Army to Meet and Receive Them from the Baſſa, ſent with ſome Troops from hence, that ſo the Reſpect and Safety of Ambaſſadors, obſerved by all Nations, as is fit and neceſſary, may remain in its Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Luſtre; therefore You know how careful both Sides ought to be of their ſafe Paſſage: For the reſt, Proſperity be to thoſe that ſhall follow the True Direction.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Given in Our Army near <hi>Niſſa.</hi>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed> Signed, <hi>Oſman</hi> Baſſa of <hi>Aleppo.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:152466:9"/>
            <p>To this Letter, the Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> after ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting the Matter in Council, with the Chief Officers of the Army, returned the following Anſwer:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>
                        <hi>Maximilian Emanuel,</hi> &amp;c. To <hi>Oſman,</hi> Baſſa, Greeting, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WE have Received the Letter You ſent <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s from the Camp near</hi> Niſſa, <hi>wherein You give <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s to underſtand, That an Ambaſſador, by Name</hi> Sulſicar Effendi, <hi>and the firſt</hi> Drugger-man, <hi>have Orders from your Emperor to come to Our Army; Now, although we being Inclin'd to Military Actions, might well refuſe their coming hither; or which, none could take amiſs, in the preſent Juncture of Affairs, might put it off till another time, ſince We do judge their Propoſals will little agree with Our preſent Intentions; yet, being moved by a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Compaſſion, We do grant that They may come to Our Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and We will favourably Hear what Your Emperor has Commanded them to Propoſe unto <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s; for which purpoſe, We have Commanded that a Paſsport be prepared for Their ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and delivered to the Perſon that brought <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s your Letter: We have likewiſe given Order to the Commandant of</hi> Semen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria, <hi>that in the manner directed him, and with a ſufficient number of Troops, he Conduct them ſafely to Our Army, upon which they may firmly Rely.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Given in our Camp before <hi>Belgrade,</hi> &amp;c.</dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Upon the return of this Anſwer to the Baſſa of <hi>Aleppo</hi>'s Letter, General <hi>Caraffa</hi> received Orders to go to <hi>Titul,</hi> to meet the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Ambaſſadors, and to hear what they had to Propoſe; and in the mean while the Elector of <hi>Bavaria</hi> ſent to <hi>Vienna,</hi> to acquaint the Emperor that a <hi>Chiaux</hi> was
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152466:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>Arrived in the Camp, and what he had done in Anſwer to the Letter received, deſiring further Advice on this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion; upon which, he received Directions to ſuffer the Ambaſſadors to paſs on with their Train: So that the <hi>Chiaux</hi> was ſent back with a Paſs-port for the Ambaſſadors, under the Convoy of Twenty Horſe: And thereupon the Count <hi>de Lodron</hi> Marched with a Regiment of <hi>Croats,</hi> to ſtrengthen the Garriſon a little before put into <hi>Semandria,</hi> leaſt the <hi>Turks</hi> ſhould return, upon ſecond Thoughts, and Repoſſeſs it.</p>
            <p>On the Twenty Fifth, the great Canon being Arrived, and the Batteries were Intirely fixed, the Beſiegers poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed themſelves under the favour of them of another <hi>Moſque,</hi> very advantageouſly Scituate, to ſhelter them in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing their Works, whilſt the Miners Lodged themſelves at the Foot of the Wall, and made Lodgments for their Powder.</p>
            <p>On the Twenty Sixth, the Batteries againſt the Caſtle Playing furiouſly, beat down the Top of the Round-Tower, which fell into the Ditch, doing damage to the Battlements, and other Works in its Fall; and the better to forward this good Succeſs, Fifteen Mortars were placed moſt advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geouſly on the ſides of the Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ries that were the moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced, in order to caſt Bomb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto the Caſtle and Town.</p>
            <p>On the Twenty Seventh the Canon and Mortars Play'd very furiouſly, by whoſe continual Thundering, a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Breach was made in the Wall, at what Time the Beſieged ſprung a Mine near the <hi>Moſque,</hi> of which the Beſiegers made themſelves the laſt Maſters; which, though it did not Blow up, yet rendered it uſeleſs, and Wounded di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Men that were in and near it.</p>
            <p>On the Twenty Eighth, The Beſieged ſprung another Mine, deſigning thereby to Ruine the main Advance Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery of the Beſiegers; but Blowing up ſhort, it only ſhook
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152466:10"/>it, without any Demoliſhment; yet the Thunder-crack was ſo great, that it occaſioned a conſiderable Diſorder, and was Increaſed by one of the Beſieged's Bombs, ſetting Fire to ſeveral Quintals of Powder, which blew up Seven or Eight Men that were on the Battery; which the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged perceiving, made a Sally with about an Hundred Men, coming on the Right and Left of the Head of the Trenches, but found the Guards there in ſo good a Poſture, that being warmly received (after ſome Diſpute) they were beaten back, with the loſs of Twelve of their Men, who were Killed at the firſt Volley of Shot diſcharged upon them: And this day Two <hi>Chriſtians</hi> made their Eſcape out of the Place, to the Camp; and declared, That the Garriſon was between Three and Four Thouſand ſtrong, that they were very diligent in Mining, to meet the Approaches of the Beſiegers; and that the Governor, whoſe Name was <hi>Ibraim,</hi> aſſured them there was a Powerful Army coming to their Relief; Incouraging them, in the Expectation thereof, to make a reſolute Defence.</p>
            <p>On the Twenty Ninth, His Electoral Highneſs ſent a Captain, with an Interpreter, to Summon the Beſieged to a Surrender of the Town and Caſtle, ſeeing they could have no hopes, or the leaſt expectation of Succour; which the Governor ſo highly reſent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that (contrary to the Rules or Articles of War) he cauſed the Interpreter, who was a <hi>Grecian,</hi> to be Hanged, and Impriſoned the Captain. The Night following, the Beſiegers Engineers ſet Fire to the Beſieged's Paliſado's, and thereupon a Detachment of not Men were ordered to advance, and make a Lodgment in the Ditch; but the Beſieged, by the light of this Fire, ſo well directed and levelled their Shot, that 100 of the Party were Killed, a great many Wounded, and the reſt obliged to retire, notwithſtanding the Fire ſo ruined the Paliſado's, that being within the reach of the Shot from the Trenches, the Beſieged could not Repair them.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:152466:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>On the Thirtieth, The Fury of the Canon had very much enlarged the Breach; but however, it was not judged open enough for an Aſſault, and the Miners having run a Mine to the Corner of one of the largeſt Towers on the Wall, and heightning Themſelves in expectation of the great uſe they might make of it, found themſelves diſappointed by a Countermine made againſt them by the Beſieged, into which they unadviſedly fell, and were ſo annoyed with Granado's and combuſtible Matter that was Fired, to put a ſtop to their Progreſs, that to avoid the danger and the ſtench, they found themſelves conſtrained to retire towards the opening of their own Mine, with ſome Loſs: And the ſame day the Prince of <hi>Savoy</hi> was Wounded in the Thigh with a Muſquet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhot; and ſome time before, Major General <hi>Aſpremont,</hi> with the fall of an Old Wall, and ſeveral others of leſſer Note.</p>
            <p>On the Thirty Firſt, The Canon continued to Play on both Sides very furiouſly, with very good Effect on the part of the Beſiegers; nor were the Beſieged Idle, but proceeded with great Endeavours, and indefatigable Induſtry, with Earth, Faggots, and other Materials to make up the Breaches, and to Intrench themſelves within them; however, the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiegers ſo far Advanced, that they, in a manner, formed their Gallery, and appeared every where deſirous to give the Aſſault, though about this time (without any juſt Ground) the Camp was Alarumed by the Country People, through a Report ſpread abroad, that there were Powerful Armies of <hi>Turks</hi> approaching; but whilſt every Body was wondring from whence they ſhould come, all that could be gathered was, that <hi>Teckley,</hi> who with ſmall Parties was wandring about the Neighbourhood of <hi>Semendria,</hi> had bribed ſome, and deceived others into this Opinion; whereupon a Body of Horſe was ſent out in ſearch of him; and the Scouts that came in brought a certain account, that <hi>Oſman Teghen</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained at <hi>Niſſa</hi> with his Horſe, moſt of his Infantry having,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152466:11"/>upon Diſcontents, want of Pay, and for other Reaſons, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted him; however, he continued to deſtroy all the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and Burn the Towns for above Forty Miles in circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference; yet, ſo great was the Plenty in the Imperial Camp, that a Fat-Oxe might be bought for a Duccate; and even at <hi>Vienna</hi> it ſelf Proviſions could not be Purchaſed at ſo cheap a Rate; one main Reaſon for it being the Three Bridges, that gave free Forrage and Communication on all ſides, <hi>viz.</hi> One over the <hi>Save,</hi> Another over the <hi>Thyſſe,</hi> and a Third over the <hi>Danube,</hi> a little above <hi>Belgrade:</hi> And now, upon the News of the Duke of <hi>Lorain</hi>'s Arrival at <hi>Peter Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radine,</hi> His Electoral Highneſs ſent thither to Complement him upon His coming into <hi>Hungary,</hi> ſince the Recovery of His late Indiſpoſition.</p>
            <p>On the Firſt of <hi>September,</hi> the Canon from Six Batteries and Thirty Two Mortars, Played upon the Caſtle, widen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Breach, and doing conſiderable Execution; under the favour of which, the Beſiegers began to fill up the Ditch, preparing ſeveral Mines to be uſeful towards a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Aſſault: And Major General <hi>Dunwalt</hi> Marched out with Twelve Regiments of Horſe towards <hi>Semendria,</hi> to ſeize upon, and ſecure ſuch part of the Country as remained Unharraſed, or not Deſtroyed by the <hi>Turks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the Second, the Canon ruined the Beſieged's Batteries, and the Defences they had made within the Breaches, by way of Reintrenchments, ſo that the Breach was conceived wide enough to Enter; yet the Beſieged continued Obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, refuſing to return any Anſwer to the Summons ſent them, on the Twenty Ninth of <hi>Auguſt;</hi> and ſeemed rather to expect the laſt Extremity, than think of terms of Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by way of Capitulation, and timely Surrender; whereupon it was concluded, that the Town and Caſtle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made Saultable, no time ſhould be loſt in carrying it on with the utmoſt Courage and Vigour; ſo that the Third,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152466:11"/>Fourth, and Fifth days being ſpent in Battering the yet remaining Works, Springing ſome Mines, and filling the Ditch to facilitate the Aſcent, and giving neceſſary Orders as to what was intended in the Execution, without any great diſturbance from the Beſieged, though ſeveral were Killed and Wounded.</p>
            <p>On the Sixth, the day appointed for the General Aſſault, (incouraged by their Commanders) after ſome Diſpute, in which many were Killed and Wounded, the Soldiers mounted the Breach, where the Beſieged, with great Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, made an Obſtinate Reſiſtance, and defended it with ſo much Vigour, (Fighting like Men in Deſpair, for the laſt Refuge and defence of their Lives) that the Beſiegers were twice beaten off: But the Elector himſelf, not ſparing his Perſon in places of Eminent danger, being at hand, and animating the Officers and Soldiers upon the Third Aſſault, the Beſieged finding all their Effort and Oppoſition vain, began to loſe Courage, and, by degrees, to Retire; ſo that perceiving the Breach, and all their Retrenchments, on that part, intirely won, they abandoned the Fight, and fled to the Caſtle, as the place of their laſt Retreat; but the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiegers now entring like a Torrent, preſſing on with great Fury, entered pell-mell with them, putting all (in the firſt heat, without diſtinction of Age and Sex) to the Sword, nor could the Riches they offered prevail to the ſaving their Lives; which the Baſſa perceiving, and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no hopes of making any long Reſiſtance, he cauſed Three Hundred Chriſtian Slaves to be brought, Chained together, which he placed before the retiring <hi>Turks,</hi> in ſuch manner as they muſt have received the Shot made at the Enemy; in compaſſion to whom, the Soldiers ſtopped in the heat of Blood, and the Elector Commanded that Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhould be given; whereupon, about Five Hundred <hi>Turks,</hi> that (under the favour of this Stratagem) had ſaved
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152466:12"/>themſelves, together with the Baſſa Governor, and Two other Baſſa's, ſubmitted, and were made Priſoners of War, with many that were not in Arms; when as the Baſſa Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor being brought to the Preſence of the Elector of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varia,</hi> he fell proſtrate before him, and made it his earneſt Requeſt, that he might not be made a Priſoner; (the <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garians,</hi> and <hi>Raſcians,</hi> returning him extraordinary Thanks for ſaving their Lives); to which humble Requeſt, His Electoral Highneſs, replyed, <hi>That he ſhould experience, the Chriſtians uſe their Priſoners better than the Turks do;</hi> adding withal, That he ſhould be immediately ſent to the Emperor, at which he ſeemed extreamly pleaſed; and thereupon General <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raffa,</hi> who had it in charge to carry the Propoſals made by the <hi>Turks,</hi> was Commanded to take charge of him, and Guard him to <hi>Newſtadt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The greateſt Prizes that were gained in the Sack of this Important Place, fell to the ſhare of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Slaves, who knew where their Maſters had hid their Treaſure, during the Siege; of which, there were found about Six Hundred, the greater part of them <hi>Auſtrians,</hi> who had at ſumdry times been taken by <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Parties, and brought or Sold to the <hi>Turks,</hi> Inhabitants of the City, and now found their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very from a long and cruel Bondage, by the prevailing Arms of their fellow Chriſtians: here were found likewiſe Seventy Pieces of Canon, great and ſmall; and although the Town and Caſtle was extreamly defaced by Fire, yet the Houſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many of them ruinous before, and the greater part built with Timber, will, upon their Rebuilding, render them more Famous; which will not long be wanting, by reaſon of its Commodious Scituation for Trade, and confluence of People that are ſoon expected thither from their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Parts.</p>
            <p>This Action laſted Four hours, with much Blood-ſhed and Slaughter on both Sides, moſt of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Garriſon
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152466:12"/>Soldiers being Killed, a Thouſand dead Bodies being after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward found, and thrown into the River, and Three Thouſand made Priſoners; nor was the number of the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſlain in the Aſſault, inconſiderable, among whom, of more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Note (in relation to their Characters and Quality) fell Lieutenant General Count <hi>D' Schariffenburg;</hi> the Count <hi>Emanuel d' Fruſtemburg,</hi> Colonel of Foot; and the Young Count <hi>d'Staremberg;</hi> ſo unto the Governor of <hi>Vienna,</hi> many likewiſe of Note were Wounded, amongſt whom, the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector of <hi>Bavaria</hi> himſelf ſlightly in the Cheek, as he expoſed his Perſon in places of danger, to Incourage the Aſſailants, and give neceſſary Orders.</p>
            <p>And thus in the ſpace of Twenty Two days the Famous City of <hi>Belgrade,</hi> fell into the Hands of the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and by its Reduction, opened them a way into all the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Dominions that are conſiderable in <hi>Europe;</hi> there being no Place of great Importance between it and <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> the Metropolis of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire, which (if the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtine Commotions of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Princes hinder not) may undoubtedly, in a ſhort time, follow the Fortune of this ſtrong City; as alſo their other places got, and unjuſtly detained from the <hi>European</hi> Chriſtians, to the ſhaking, if not the Overthrow of that Bloody Empire, which (for upward of Two Hundred Years) has been ſo terrible to Chriſtendom.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Three</hi> B<hi>'s, of which Two are already won,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Will Crown the Glory of the Work begun.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Buda, Belgrade, Bizantum <hi>once obtain'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The reſt will be but ſport, and quickly gain'd.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:152466:13"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>SInce the Rendition of this Important Place, more particular News came of the Defeat of the Baſſa of</hi> Boſnia, <hi>which, for the extraordinary and unexpected ſucceſs of the Chriſtians, I conceived might be acceptable, and not improper to be added: Prince</hi> Lovis <hi>of</hi> Baden <hi>on the Fourth of</hi> Septemb. <hi>having notice that four or five Thouſand</hi> Turks <hi>were Encamped about Six Miles from</hi> Brod, <hi>he Marched to Encounter them with</hi> 3000 <hi>Horſe and Dragoons, Marching with great diligence all Night, but in the Morning (to his no ſmall Surprize) he found himſelf greatly miſ-inform'das to the Number, which amounted to Fifteen Thouſand Horſe and Foot; under the Command of the Baſſa: however, calling the Officers about him, he told them, it was to no purpoſe to think of Retreating, as being too late, by reaſon of their too far Engagement amongst the Enemy, but that they muſt now fight for their Lives and Victory, which was chearfully conſented to; but before they had well put themſelves into a Poſture to Fight, the</hi> Turks <hi>had ſurrounded them, and vigorouſly charged four or five times, which was ſuſtained with ſo much Bravery, and ſuch vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous Returns, that the Enemies Horſe perceiving
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152466:13"/>themſelves over-ſet, fell first into Diſorder, and then to open Flight, leaving the Foot to ſhift for themſelves, whoſe Ranks being forced (by the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Horſe breaking in upon them) they were mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably Beaten down and Slain, thoſe that Fled, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out for Quarter; ſo the Prince becoming entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Maſter of the Field,</hi> 5000 <hi>of the</hi> Turks <hi>were found kill'd,</hi> 2000 <hi>taken Priſoners,</hi> 36 <hi>Colours taken, and all the Baggage; for which extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Succeſs, (in which the hand of God ſo ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally appear'd) Thanks were ſent up to Heaven in moſt of the Capital Cities of the Empire. We are further aſſured, that of the</hi> 1000 <hi>Boats that fled from</hi> Belgrade, <hi>before and after it was Inveſted, not above</hi> 200 <hi>of them Arrived in places of Safety, the reſt being either Stranded, bedded in the Mudd for want of Water, or Deſerted by ſuch as were in them, out of a fear they were Purſued, and by that means moſt of the Deſerters with their Baggage fell into the hands of the Country people, or ſuch parties as were abroad to ſcowre the Coaſt, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Spoil,</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
